A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Robert H. Edwards FA566
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Robert H. Edwards
1968-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Edwards, Robert H. (Robert Hazard), 1935-
Ford Foundation
FA566
3.28 Cubic Feet 8 LTR size and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger boxes
Robert H. (Hazard) Edwards joined the Ford Foundation as a program officer for the International Division in 1965. In 1968, Mr. Edwards served as the Foundation's Representative in Pakistan. He later transferred to the Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program in the early 1970s where he would serve as Deputy Head under William Fredericks. In 1973, he succeeded Fredericks as MEA Head. Mr. Edwards left the Foundation in 1977 to accept an appointment as President of Carleton College in Northfield, Minnesota. The Office Files of Robert H. Edwards span from 1968 to 1977 and comprise the files that Mr. Edwards kept as Head of the International Division's MEA Program. The collection is organized into three series: program management files, subject files, and chronological files. The program management files primarily consist of memoranda but also correspondence, notes, reports, and papers relating to the work of Mr. Edwards's program officer Lowell S. Hardin. Mr. Edwards's subject files contain memoranda, correspondence, papers, speeches, reports, meeting materials, and background primarily pertaining to the Foundation's programs in the Middle East and Africa. His chronological files of correspondence and memoranda from the year 1968 and the years between 1972 and 1977 are also available.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
A later set of Robert H. Edwards Staff Subject Files was transferred to the RAC in March 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:019. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in April 2019.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical Note
Robert H. (Hazard) Edwards was born on May 26, 1935 in London, England and was raised in Middleton, Ohio. In 1957, he received a B.A. in English from Princeton University. He subsequently read law at Cambridge University and received an LL.B. from Harvard Law School in 1961.
After graduation, Mr. Edwards served under the Queen's Commissioner in the Bechuanaland Protectorate from 1961 to 1963, where he assisted in its transition to independence as the Republic of Botswana. From 1963 to 1965, he worked for the U.S. State Department's Bureau of United Nations Affairs on matters relating to the newly independent African countries before joining the Ford Foundation as a program officer for the International Division in 1965. In 1968, Mr. Edwards served as the Foundation's Representative in Pakistan. He later transferred to the Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program in the early 1970s where he would serve as Deputy Head under William Fredericks. In 1973, he succeeded Fredericks as MEA Head.
Mr. Edwards left the Foundation in 1977 to accept an appointment as President of Carleton College in Northfield, Minnesota. In 1986, he left Carleton College to join the Secretariat of His Highness the Aga Khan as Head of the Department of Health, Education and Housing in Karachi, Pakistan. From 1987 to 1990, he also served on the Board of Trustees of Aga Khan University. He returned to the United States in 1990, serving as President of Bowdoin College until his retirement in 2001.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation has been engaged in overseas work since the early 1950s. The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the future. In 1951, the Foundation established two of its first grant programs, Overseas Development (OD) and Overseas Training and Research (OTR). The granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. South and Southeast Asia were the initial focus, with India and Pakistan receiving the majority of grants. A more limited number of grants were issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants also was initiated for the Near East. In 1957, Overseas Development further expanded to include programs in Latin America.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international programs such as International Training and Research (ITR) and Population, became part of a single International Division (ID). A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). DCP was again restructured in 1989, resulting in the separating of programs in Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA) as independent program areas.
Related Materials
FA547 Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Forrest F. Hill, 1952-1966 - contain related subject files on agricultural development and the establishment of agricultural research and training centers. Dr. Hill served as Vice President of Overseas Development (later International Division) from 1955 to 1963
FA503 Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Programs (AME), Program Staff Files - contain other files of Robert H. Edwards. Also included in the collection are files of Dr. John D. Gerhart, Steven M. Riskin, and Anna Wadia. The bulk of the files are meeting and discussion group records from staff participation at internal Foundation meetings and discussion groups that brought together different philanthropies for common goals.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 3 series.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Project Management Files, 1973-1976
Series 2. Subject Files, 1969-1977
Series 3. Chronological Files, 1968-1977
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Robert H. Edwards span from 1968 to 1977 and comprises the files that Mr. Edwards kept as Head of the International Division's Middle East and Africa Program. The collection is organized into three series: program management files, subject files, and chronological files.
The program management files primarily consist of memoranda but also correspondence, notes, reports and papers relating to the work of Mr. Edwards's program officer Lowell S. Hardin. As is reflected in the subjects covered in his files, Mr. Hardin's work primarily concerned agricultural research and rural development in the Middle East and Africa. His files include information on agricultural research centers, international efforts in aquaculture, the world food crisis, the difficulty in recruiting staff for Africa, the phasing out of advisory support for economic planning in Africa, and the possibility of Saudi support for agricultural research.
Mr. Edwards's subject files contain memoranda, correspondence, papers, speeches, reports, meeting materials and background primarily pertaining to the Foundation's programs in the Middle East and Africa. There are materials on the Foundation interest in and support for inter-faith dialogues in the Middle East, area studies and social science research in Africa, training for journalists in Africa, and international agricultural research and training centers. In addition, there are discussion and background papers as well as memoranda concerning the agenda and logistics for the Ford Foundation Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture held in Ibadan, Nigeria (1973). Some of the subject files pertain to the Foundation's work on legal development in Latin America and the International Legal Center (ILC) Research Advisory Committee on Law and Development. These files contain meeting materials for the ILC Research Advisory Committee and memoranda reporting on a series of in-house Foundation meetings on law and social change in Latin America (1972-1973).
A subject file on Foundation-grantee relations contains memoranda and discussion papers critiquing and reflecting on the how the Foundation interacts with grantees. Memoranda and papers address such issues as defining the limits of Foundation intervention in grantee organizations, the autonomy granted to grantees to execute projects, the responsibilities of program officers, and the status of Foundation employees hired through suballocations. These materials appear to be background for task force discussions addressing a lack of sensitivity toward grantees in Foundation policy formulation (1973).
The chronological files in the collection were expanded by the addition of a later segment of Robert H. Edwards office files (Accession 2019:019). They contain correspondence and memoranda.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Ford Foundation; Africa; Africa, Eastern; Africa, Southern; Africa, West; Bangladesh; Botswana; Egypt; Israel; Kenya; Lebanon; Middle East; Pakistan; Saudi Arabia; South Africa; Agricultural development projects -- Africa; Agricultural development projects -- Middle East; Economic development; Economic development -- Africa; Economic development -- Middle East; International relations; Race relations
- Program Management Files, 1973-1976; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of files kept by Mr. Edwards about the work of his program officer, Lowell S. Hardin. Arranged chronologically, the files contain memoranda concerning Mr. Hardin's management of grants for agriculture and rural development in the Middle East and Africa. They also report on site visits, meetings with grantees and potential grantees and conferences Mr. Hardin attended.
  - Hardin, Lowell S. -- Re: Phasing Out Advisory Support for Economic Planning in Africa, Update on World Food Situation, etc., 1973 September-November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hardin, Lowell S. -- Re: FF Agricultural Programs, Recruitment for International Development Work, etc., 1973 November-1974 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hardin, Lowell S. -- Re: Encouraging Saudi Support for Agricultural Research, International Centers Week, etc., 1974 June-September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hardin, Lowell S. -- Re: International Agricultural Research Centers, UN World Food Conference, etc., 1974 June-1975 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hardin, Lowell S. -- Re: Sudan Rural Development, Social Science Research and Competence Building in Africa, etc., 1975 September-1976 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1969-1977; 2
  The files in this series document Mr. Edwards work as Head of the Middle East and Africa Program. His subject files contain information on agricultural and social science research in Africa, inter-faith dialogues in the Middle East, and debates over a Soviet-sponsored declaration introduced at the 1976 UNESCO conference concerning the roles of the state and mass media operating within its borders. There are also files for the Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture held in Ibadan, Nigeria from February 9-10, 1973.
  A few subject files pertain to the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC) and the Foundation's policy making generally. These include files on the Foundation's law and development work in Latin America and efforts to increase sensitivity in the formulation of policies governing Foundation-grantee relationships. The files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Area Studies -- Re: MEA Luncheons/Meetings to Review Area Studies and Social Science Research, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies -- 1974 Program Activities, Summary Report, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies -- Re: Consultation and Comments on Future of the Peace Corps Study, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bundy, George -- "Towards An Open Foreign Policy" and "Private Institutions in the Public Service" (speeches), 1973 October-November (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Agenda, Logistics, Overview of FF Agricultural Programs, Background Articles, 1974 February-1975 May (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Discussion and Background Papers (1 of 5), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Discussion and Background Papers (2 of 5), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Discussion and Background Papers (3 of 5), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Discussion and Background Papers (4 of 5), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Discussion and Background Papers (5 of 5), 1974 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - FF Seminar for OLAC/MEA Program Advisors in Agriculture -- Handwritten Notes, 1974 April 29-May 3 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Foundation-Grantee Relations -- Staff Memoranda and Papers for Discussion on Policy Formulation, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Foundations -- "Private Foundations: In Search of a Purpose" (speech by Sen. Vance Hartke), 1974 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Germain, Adrienne -- Re: African Training and Research Center for Women (UN ECA), Final Report for Consultancy on Women in Bangladesh, etc., 1975 December-1976 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gremillion, Joseph -- Re: Inter-Religious Colloquium in Bellagio, Italy, Tri-Faith Dialogue Panel in Egypt, 1975 July-1976 January (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - International Agricultural Centers -- Report on Discussions of 1975 Programs and Budgets, 1974 June (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Legal Center -- Research Advisory Committee on Law and Development -- Draft Report on Next Phase of Activities, Grant Action Report, 1973 April (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - International Legal Center -- Research Advisory Committee on Law and Development Meeting, Feb 9-10, 1973 (1 of 2), 1972 December-1974 January (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - International Legal Center -- Research Advisory Committee on Law and Development Meeting, Feb 9-10, 1973 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Law and Development -- Re: Law and Social Change in Latin America, OLAC In-House Foundation Meetings, etc., 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Press in Africa -- Re: Nigerian Institute of Journalism and FF Support for Training of Journalists, Controversy Over Soviet-Sponsored UNESCO Declaration Re: Mass Media and the State, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Television -- Re: Placing FF Staff on Local Interview Shows, Proposal for Research into Impact of Television in South Africa, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Wells, Oris V. -- Re: Discussion on Improving World Food Situation Report -- Memoranda, Notes, Draft Report, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Chronological Files, 1968-1977; 3; 2.09 Cubic Feet About 5.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  This series consists of Robert H. Edward's chronological files of correspondence and memoranda. When the collection was first processed, it only contained the April to October 1968 chronological files. These files contain information about meetings with grantees or potential grantees, correspondence with grantees, grant recommendations, and some budget information.
  A later run of Edwards' chronological files was incorporated into the series when another segment of Edwards' office files was transferred to the RAC from the Ford Foundation. These files primarily originate from between 1972 and 1977 and document Edwards' time as Deputy Head and Head of the Foundation's Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program. The correspondence and memoranda in the files concern the MEA's grant giving activities in the fields of agricultural development, economic development, education, race relations, and international relations in different countries throughout the Middle East and Africa. Administrative tasks such as setting up visits to the different MEA field offices, tracking data related to different grants, and managing the MEA budget are also documented in the records.
  Program shifts in MEA organizational structure and grant giving activities due to and international political developments and budget constraints are discussed in much of Edwards' correspondence. Some materials in the Summer 1976 chronological files concern the transfer of the Middle East Regional Office headquarters from Beirut, Lebanon to Cairo, Egypt and the scaling back of the Foundation's programming in Lebanon following the recent changes in that country. Similarly, there are records in chronological files from the Spring of 1977 that regard the closing of a Foundation suboffice in Saudi Arabia as well as concerns of whether or not long-term involvement in the country would be practical. In regards to the impact of budget changes on MEA programming, there are many letters throughout the files that discuss the MEA's attempts to reexamine how it should support area studies for the Middle East and Africa.
  A less featured aspect of MEA programming featured in Edwards' chronological files is the support of African literary projects. The series holds several letters that Edwards addressed to Nigerian author, Chinua Achebe. Other subjects that Edwards' correspondence and memoranda discuss include events in Pakistan and Bangladesh in the early 1970s (Edwards was Representative for Pakistan before transferring to MEA), Arab-Israeli relations, and the development of programming for Southern Africa. While many of the documents in Edwards' later chronological files regard his departure, there is also some significant memoranda such as his memo about program directions for South Africa.
  - Chronological file, 1968 April (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Chronological file, 1968 May (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Chronological file, 1968 June (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Chronological file, 1968 July (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Chronological file, 1968 August (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Chronological file, 1968 September (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Chronological file, 1968 October (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Chronological file, 1972 March-November (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
  - Chronological file, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
  - Chronological file, 1968-1973, bulk 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Chronological file, 1973 April (Box 5, Folder 42-43)
  - Chronological file, alphabetical by addressee, 1968, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 44-47)
  - Chronological file, alphabetical by addressee, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 48-51)
  - Chronological file, alphabetical by addressee, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 52-55)
  - Chronological file, alphabetical by addressee, 1974 September-November (Box 7, Folder 56-57)
  - Chronological file, 1974 November (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Chronological file, 1974 December (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Chronological file, 1975 January (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Chronological file, 1975 January-February (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Chronological file, 1975 March (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Chronological file, 1975 April (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Chronological file, 1975 April-May (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Chronological file, 1975 June (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Chronological file, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Chronological file, 1975 August (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Chronological file, 1975 May-October (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Chronological file, 1975 September-October (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Chronological file, 1975 October-November (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Chronological file, 1975 November-December (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Chronological file, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Chronological file, 1976 January-February (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Chronological file, 1976 February-March (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Chronological file, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Chronological file, 1976 March-May (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Chronological file, 1976 March-June (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Chronological file, 1976 June-July (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Chronological file, 1976 August (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Chronological file, 1976 September-November (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Chronological file, 1976 October-November (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Chronological file, 1976 May-December (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Chronological file, 1977 January (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Chronological file, 1977 February-March (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Chronological file, 1977 April (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Chronological file, 1977 May (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Chronological file, 1977 June (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Chronological file, 1977 July (Box 9, Folder 88)